A Guide to the Gum Springs, Virginia Collection, 1915-1991
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The Gum Springs, Virginia Collection, 1915-1991
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 03-10
.5 linear feet
The Gum Springs, Virginia Collection consists of .5 linear feet and spans the years 1915-1991 and consists of correspondence, a book manuscript, consulting reports, minutes, newspaper clippings, oral interview, blue prints, and cost estimates. Subjects covered are freedman; African-American community life; Gum Springs black history museum study including related community meetings; and the War on Poverty.
Virginia Room staff
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Virginia Room staff artificially created this collection over the years. The majority of the collection came from unknown donors. Frank Kulesza donated the photocopied Colored Citizens Protection League Minutes.
Historical and Biographical Information
Gum Springs is Fairfax County’s largest African-American community. It is located at the intersection of Richmond Highway and Mount Vernon Road on the northern boundary of the original Mount Vernon property. In 1829, West Ford, an antebellum freedman, purchased the land tract that comprises most of what is now Gum Springs. Ford who was born a slave, gained his freedom under the terms of the will of Hannah Bushrod Washington, a relative of George Washington. Ford farmed his land while he continued to work and live at Mount Vernon. Similar to Ford, many of Gum Springs’ earliest black residents were associated with Mount Vernon. After the Civil War as the number of free blacks swelled, Gum Springs’ population grew. The history of the black community in Gum Springs spans over 150 years and is characterized by economic struggle and aspiration as well as African-American community building. In the 20th century, its residents struggled to maintain their rural livelihoods in the face of post-World War II suburbanization. It was the first community to receive anti-poverty funding under the federal “War on Poverty.”
In 1984, the Fairfax County Park Authority issued a Request for Proposals (RFP) for the Feasibility of Developing and Maintaining a Black History Museum in Fairfax County. The RFP solicitation specified that the museum had to be in the Gum Springs area of Fairfax County. The resulting feasibility study became known as the Gum Springs Black History Museum Study. Through the RFP process, the Center for History Now was designated as the study consultant. The scope of work included recommendations for an effective, cost-efficient concept and plan, and implementation plan, and an evaluation of its benefits. The Gum Springs Historical Society's Museum & Cultural Center opened on November 24, 1996.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
HLF Gum Springs - History; John Terry Chase Manuscript Papers on "Gum Springs: The Triumph of a Black Community" - MSS 08-22
None
Index Terms
African-American Community life; The Center for History Now; Fairfax County Park Authority; Ford, West; Freedman; Post-Civil War South; Saunders B. Moon Community Action Association
Container List
- Gum Springs Monograph - Corbin, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Gum Springs Study Correspondence, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Gum Springs Black History Study Comm. (Minutes, Notes, etc.), 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Gum Springs Study Minute Books, Notes, 1919-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Colored Citizens Protection League Minutes (photocopy), 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Gum Springs Study Newspaper Clippings, 1968-1982 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Newspaper. “Gum Springs News” [two copies], 1965 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Program - Dedication of Martin Luther King, Jr. Park, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Gum Springs Historical Society, Bethlehem Baptist Church, 1865-1990 brochure, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Gum Springs, VA - Dedication of Historical Marker, programs, 1991 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Gum Springs Feasibility Study - Black History Museum, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Saunders, Mrs. Bruce. Oral Interview., 1968 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 12)